A Guide to the Charles P. Deyerle Papers, 1842-1855
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
Charles P. Deyerle Papers, 1842-1855
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
mss 00191
The papers consist of 12 items.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Deyerle Papers were donated to the Virginia Military Institute in two parts. Four items were received from Frank H. Hammond, Jr. in 1957. Additional items were donated by Howard R. Hammond in 1992.
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles Peter Deyerle was born on November 8, 1820 in Roanoke County, Virginia, the son of Joseph Deyerle and Anne Crawford. Deyerle was a member of the first graduating class of the Virginia Military Institute, receiving his diploma in July 1842. He subsequently studied medicine at the University of Pennsylvania and received a commission in the United States Army. As an army surgeon, he served in the Mexican War and was afterwards assigned to Benicia Barracks in California. He died in California on October 30, 1853; in 1855 his body was returned to Salem, Virginia and is buried in East Hill Cemetery.
Scope and Content Information
The papers contain 12 items from the career of Charles P. Deyerle. Included are documents dating from his medical studies and his service in the United States Army. Also included are miscellaneous clippings.
Additional Descriptive Dada
Separated Material
A daguerreotype of Charles P. Deyerle has been catalogued separately and is located in the VMI Archives Photograph Collection.
Contents List
- Drawing, VMI. 1842
  Pencil sketch depicting the Virginia Military Institute as it was during Deyerle's cadetship.
- Bible verse, holograph. circa 1842
  VMI Superintendent Francis H. Smith to Charles P. Deyerle: Bible verse in Smith's hand given as "a token of affection...."
- Notebook. 1844-1845
  Containing notes from medical school lectures at the University of Pennsylvania, as well as misc. clippings.
- Letter of Recommendation. 1846 April 3
  Signed by the medical faculty of the University of Pennsylvania.
- University of Pennsylvania Medical School Diploma. 1846
- War Department Form Letter. 1846 June 3
  Informing Deyerle of the examination for appointment as an army surgeon.
- U. S. Army Commission Document. 1847 February
  Deyerle's commission as assistant surgeon.
- Notebook. 1849 March
  Travel notes written at Rio de Janiero and at sea off coast of South America.
- Newspaper, Daily American Star(Mexico). 1848 January 6
  Single issue.
- Newspaper, Salem Weekly Register(Salem, VA). 1855 April 19.
  Single issue. Top bears signature of "Miss Susan P. Deyerle."
- Clippings, Misc.
- Book, Poland under the Dominion of Russia. 1834
  Bears signature of C. P. Deyerle.
- Book, Fresh Gleanings; or a New Sheaf from the Old Fields. 1851
  From the library of C. P. Deyerle.